One quarter of all the land on Earth
is covered by a single,
remarkable type of plant.
Almost indestructible, it can
grow two feet in a day...
..and be tall enough
to hide a giant.
LOW RUMBLING
That plant is grass, and the
world it creates is truly unique.
The grass in northern India
is the tallest on the planet,
home to some of the most impressive
creatures to tread the Earth.
GRUNTING
These are the good times,
but in just a few months,
all this fresh growth will be gone
and the animals
will be forced to move on.
That is the way things are on
grasslands across the planet.
BIRDS TWEET
A cycle of abundance,
destruction and rebirth
that affects every creature
that lives here.
LOW RUMBLING
The largest grassland on Earth,
the vast Eurasian Steppe,
stretches one third of the way
around our planet.
Spring rain has brought fresh grass
and, with it, new life.
A relic from the ice age,
a baby saiga antelope,
just three hours old.
His only company, his twin.
Until they can stand, their mother
has left them hidden in the grass.
They should be safe,
as long as they remain quiet.
HE BLEATS
For these calves, the clock
is already ticking.
Their herd will soon be moving on,
seeking the freshest, new grass.
BLEATING
HE BLEATS
Their lanky legs are a sure sign
that they're built for a life
on the move.
HE BLEATS
BLEATING
Saiga always give birth to twins,
so their numbers grow rapidly
just when grass is plentiful.
Their bizarrely shaped nose can
detect fresh growth
from hundreds of miles away.
BLEATING
The young twins will now begin
the nomadic life they share with
most animals on the
world's open plains.
Grasslands occur where rain is too
sporadic for forests to exist.
THUNDER RUMBLES
WIND WHOOSHES
The rain that a grassland needs
to survive for a year
might arrive all at once.
CRASHING AND RUMBLING
Storms like these can release
12 inches of rain in 24 hours.
Not much fun if you're out in it.
Eventually, the Earth
can't soak up any more...
RUMBLING
..and the grassland
undergoes a radical change.
Many plants would drown here,
but grasses thrive.
They grow so fast,
their leaves quickly rise above
the water and into the sunlight.
BIRDS TWEET
Here in southern Africa,
water transforms one of the most
remarkable grasslands on Earth.
The Okavango.
Every year, 5,000 square miles
of grassland are flooded.
For one pride of lions,
this poses a major problem.
There may be plenty of prey around,
but lions struggle
to run it down in water.
CUBS MEOW
If their mothers
don't make a kill soon,
the cubs might not survive the week.
But fuelled by the flood,
the eruption of grass
attracts new possible prey.
Buffalo arrive in herds
2,000 strong.
Powerful, aggressive and united,
they're the most dangerous animal
a lion can face.
HE GRUNTS
The biggest bulls don't run.
They're simply too huge
to be scared of lions.
At 900 kilos, he weighs more
than all five lionesses combined.
The pride do have
numbers on their side...
..but one sweep of his horns
could be deadly.
One distracts the bull up front,
while her sisters attack
from behind.
The cats must somehow topple the
buffalo, but with swamp underfoot,
they can't get any traction.
LIONS ROAR
The bull is weakening...
..but the lions are tiring too.
It's now a battle of will
as much as strength.
To live, the bull must somehow
shake off the lioness.
The bull is wounded, but thanks
to his two-inch-thick hide,
he will recover.
For the pride,
these are hungry times.
CUB SQUEAKS
But ultimately,
once the water recedes,
there will be new life and new food
to benefit all.
In the right conditions,
grasses have the extraordinary
ability to grow from
first shoots to flower
in a matter of only days.
Grasses become the miniature
equivalents of fruiting trees.
And, for creatures living
within the grass,
this is a landscape as vast and
towering as any rainforest.
An excellent place to
build a tiny treehouse...
..for a harvest mouse.
During summer, European meadowlands
are full of food...
..but only for those
that can reach it.
Climbing grass is harder
than climbing trees,
not least because their stems
just won't stay still.
A prehensile tail acts
like a fifth limb,
so she's as agile as a monkey
clambering around in a tree.
STEM 'CREAKS'
And just as well, for the best food
in this tiny forest
is at the very top of its canopy.
Feeding up here, she's exposed.
A barn owl.
Not her finest move...
..but it did the trick.
Harvest mice seldom go all the way
down to the ground.
It's a tangled and dangerous world
down here.
But she can read the pattern of
the stems overhead like a map,
and so find her way home.
And not a minute too soon.
There are mouths to feed.
Her babies must fatten up quickly.
They need to harvest the
summer grasses
while they're still rich with food.
On the African savanna, too,
seasonal grasses
are filled with life,
but it won't last long.
Carmine bee-eaters are
superb aerial hunters...
..experts at catching insects
in mid-air.
But they have no way of flushing
their prey out of the grass.
INSECTS HUM AND CLICK
Once alarmed, most insects stay put.
The bee-eaters need someone
to stir things up a bit.
A kori bustard.
It's the world's
heaviest flying bird,
so it should be bulky enough
to kick up some insects.
BUZZING
Bingo!
Until someone else comes along...
..and cramps your style.
Never mind.
Perhaps there are
bigger opportunities ahead.
What about an ostrich?
The heaviest bird of all.
This time, there's more
than enough transport to go around.
Soon, almost every ostrich has
its own passenger.
But free riders are
only tolerated for so long.
What the bee-eaters really need
is a creature so big,
it won't even notice them.
SNORTING
LOW RUMBLING
Nothing cuts a swathe through grass
like an African bull elephant.
ELEPHANT GROWLS
The trick is to fly as close to the
front of the giant as possible.
They only have a split second
to grab the prize.
As more insects are stirred up,
the competition intensifies.
BIRDS CHIRP
With summer drawing to a close,
the race to stock up is on.
Soon the grass will wither, and
this opportunity will have gone.
As the dry season takes hold,
food becomes increasingly thin
on the ground.
Now, only the most specialised
predators on the plains
can make a living.
She may be spotted like a cheetah,
but this cat is no sprinter.
Instead, she has extra long legs,
which give her a high vantage point.
But a serval cat's main weapon
are enormous radar ears.
RUSTLING
They help her pinpoint prey
hiding in the grass.
But the prey she seeks are canny.
Southern vlei rats.
They know that any sustained
movement can give them away.
So they move in short bursts.
But even the slightest rustle
will give her a clue.
Warm.
Warmer.
Missed.
RUSTLING
BIRD TWEETS
SQUEAKING
In better times,
she could catch ten a day.
But now, with so few rodents around,
she will have to go hungry.
As drought intensifies,
life gets tougher for all.
Predators with permanent territories
must tough it out,
while most of their prey disappear
over the horizon.
GRUNTING AND MOOING
To avoid starvation, many grassland
animals follow
a nomadic way of life.
Over two million wildebeest wander
the East African savannas,
chasing the rains.
And they are not alone.
Arriving on the wing, Jackson's
widowbirds also seek fresh grass.
Although, it's not just food
that they're after.
This male wants a mate.
He's grown elaborate
breeding plumage for this moment.
But he needs a stage
on which to show it off.
By carefully selecting grass blades,
each trimmed to the correct length,
he's creating something
very special.
He needs an even surface...
..and a centrepiece.
The stage is set.
The problem is, can she see it?
BIRDS TWEET
He has competition.
TWEETING
It might take more than a little
gardening to impress the ladies.
Jumping is the right idea...
..but he's misjudged
the height of the grass.
TWEETING
His rival makes it look easy.
Time to raise his game.
TWEETING
It's not only who jumps the highest,
but who can keep doing
so the longest.
Unable to go the distance, his
rivals drop out one by one.
Stamina has won him admirers.
Now he can show off
his courtship arena.
And engage in a little romantic
hide-and-seek.
Finally, he's done enough.
The East African savannas
support millions of grazers.
Each year, they devour
millions of tonnes of grass.
And yet, there's one creature here
whose impact is far greater
than all these animals combined.
They're found wherever
grass grows on the planet.
Yet their labours go
almost entirely unnoticed.
One of the most remarkable
is found here,
on the grasslands of South America.
These blades are so tough
that virtually no large grass eaters
can stomach them.
Yet, they are harvested
on an industrial scale...
..by tiny grass-cutter ants.
But they themselves
can't digest one bit of it.
So, why bother?
The answer is underground.
And it's very ingenious.
Each blade is cut to length and
placed into a garden of fungus.
The rotting grass feeds the fungus
and, in turn,
the fungus feeds the ants.
But feeding five million workers
requires intensive agriculture.
Luckily, they are
an industrious lot.
This colony alone will collect over
half a tonne of grass every year.
With billions of ant colonies
across the world's grasslands
all doing exactly the same thing,
that's a mind-boggling
amount of grass.
will be harvested by an insect.
In northern Australia,
termites memorialise their industry
in sculpture.
These astonishing mounds
are ten feet tall.
They're always built
on a north-south axis
which is why their builders
are called compass termites.
These castles of clay protect
their builders from extremes of heat
and seasonal floods
experienced on many grasslands.
Termites manage to do
what most grass eaters can't -
break down dead grass
and extract the nutrients.
But they themselves can be food
for those that can reach them.
A two-foot-long tongue...
..covered in microscopic hooks...
..followed by claws
longer than those of a velociraptor.
A giant anteater
on the plains of South America.
It can devour
20,000 insects a day.
Powerful forelegs enable it to
rip apart a termite hill with ease.
And, as the sun bakes the grass,
the termites face new danger.
In minutes,
fire turns grassland to ash.
But the grasses are not dead.
Their underground stems are
unharmed.
Weeks, months may pass
but, eventually,
the rains will return
and the grass will sprout again.
Some grasslands must endure
not only fire, but ice.
BISON GROWLS
In summer, bison roamed freely,
almost continuously cropping
the abundant green grass.
Now that grass is not only withered
and frozen, it's about to be buried.
GRUNTING
60 million tonnes of snow now
blanket this herd's territory.
Pushing through deep snow
is exhausting work
and the bison
are now slowly starving.
Just keeping warm
saps huge amounts of energy.
GROWLING
Their thick coats can insulate them
down to minus 20 Fahrenheit.
It's now minus 40.
The only thing
that will keep them alive
is buried beneath
three feet of snow.
And that's a problem shared
with a surprising neighbour.
The food the fox seeks
is also deep beneath the snow.
GROWLING
The survival of both creatures
depends on getting through
to the ground.
For the bison, it will be
a matter of brute strength.
Massive neck muscles enable them
to shovel five tonnes of snow a day.
Their lightweight neighbour
needs more precision.
BISON GROWLS
The bison have reached their goal.
A mouthful of withered grass.
And where the bison have dug,
the fox now spots an opportunity.
Every footstep counts.
But he mustn't break through...
yet.
He listens carefully
to pinpoint his target.
It's moving.
A vole.
Small,
but 100 times more nutritious
than a mouthful of dried grass.
To get through the winter
on these prairies,
sometimes brain beats brawn.
Ultimately, life on all grasslands
depends on the turn of the seasons.
500 miles further north
than any tree can survive,
grass returns to life.
Caribou females have journeyed
to the far north to calve.
Over 70,000 caribou babies
will be born in the next few days.
As the calves appear, so too do the
leaves of the newly-sprouting grass.
And the calves
must strengthen quickly.
Within days, they will have
to keep up with their parents
on a never-ending march.
At one-day-old, they are already
faster than an Olympic sprinter.
They are testing the legs that
will carry them thousands of miles.
Better to learn
their limitations now.
CALF HONKS
It may look playful, but there's
no harder life on the grasslands
than that facing these infants.
The caribou mothers
now join together,
each with an infant
exactly the same age.
They're setting off on the greatest
overland trek made by any animal.
But wherever grass eaters travel,
predators lie in wait.
Here they are.
Arctic wolves.
They must seize their chance
while the caribou
pass through their territory.
CARIBOU GRUNTS
The wolf runs at the herd, trying
to flush out the weak or the slow.
A calf is separated.
At full tilt, 40-miles-an-hour,
the wolf is just faster.
But the calf has stamina.
Only a few weeks old
and this calf's will to survive
is remarkable.
And it needs to be,
for these young caribou
have now started a journey
that will last a lifetime...
..forever chasing the seasonal
growth of the grass
on which they depend.
Like all grassland creatures,
they are at the mercy
of these unpredictable,
but ultimately bountiful lands.
Grass can survive some of
the harshest conditions on Earth -
flood, fire, and frost -
and still flourish.
So it is, the grasslands
provide a stage
for the greatest gatherings
of wildlife on planet Earth.
For the grasslands team, no location
would prove as challenging
as that dominated by elephant grass
in north-east India.
The aim, to capture intimate images
of some of the world's
most elusive creatures
using the latest technology.
But they will need to be careful.
ELEPHANT TRUMPETS
More people are killed
by wildlife here in Kaziranga...
ELEPHANT ROARS
..than in any other national park
on the planet.
Every time we go into these tunnels,
we have to take an armed guard
because there are so many animals
in here that are dangerous.
Tigers are probably
the least of our worries.
But rhinos and buffalo, elephants,
sloth bear - all of them
can injure you
and we've got to keep up
with our armed guard!
The team have bumped
into their first obstacle.
There's a rhino right there.
Let's go back, because it's too
risky
going through this heavy grass.
Let's get in the open.
Another rhino.
Now we have two rhinos.
Let's get in here.
GUARD SHOUTS
OK.
The guard throws a ball of mud
to one side of the rhinos,
moving the animals on without
harming them.
OK, it's gone. OK.
What about the other one?
Let's go, quick.
With the rhinos
now a safe distance away,
the crew focus on the best spots
to position their camera traps.
I love that tunnel. The effect.
Over 100 scaffold poles
provide the anchor points
for these secret cameras.
When an animal triggers
an infrared beam,
the cameras will switch on
automatically and start recording.
If it works,
the remote-control cameras
should capture close-up footage
without disturbing the animals
or putting the crew at risk.
Basically, that's about as much
like grass as we can make it look.
As night falls, the crew
head back to base for safety.
It's time for the new technology
to prove its worth.
At dawn, the crew have
a whodunnit mystery on their hands.
Oh, wow!
That's carnage.
This looks like elephant, we think.
This is scaffold pole, huh.
They have bent... Look at that!
It's a sad day.
You win some, you lose some
and, this time,
the animals have outsmarted us.
And, in fact, check this out!
Woohoo!
So, this is our little army of
guards, protecting our trigger box.
Do they bite? These ones?
Do they bite? Sting?
Argh! Argh. Ow! Oh.
These little... BLEEP!
While Chadden irons out the bugs,
Sandesh has met some grumpy locals.
Wild Asian water buffalo
have extraordinary senses.
Mothers will charge
if they feel threatened.
The guard carries a gun
in case a warning shot is needed,
and with good reason.
More people are killed by buffalo
than by any other animal
in Kaziranga.
GUARD SHOUTS A WARNING
That will wake you up
in the morning!
Many of the park staff
have cautionary tales about buffalo.
HE SPEAKS IN HIS LANGUAGE
The buffalo caught him here.
Through his throat, and the horn
came out through his mouth
and flung him, before running away.
If the wildlife
is unfriendly to humans...
..it's proving downright hostile
to camera traps.
Completely ripped-out
the scaffold poles.
They've torn the triggers.
While Chadden is convinced
it's elephants,
the rest of the crew
are not so sure.
That's huge!
It's almost like a human footprint.
You can see the front paw,
the rear paw.
We are now two weeks in
and it's very frustrating.
I've never actually been anywhere
where the animals
go after your equipment
and destroy it, more than here.
It's time for the team
to do some detective work.
Here is our little security camera.
If any animals are coming through
and vandalising our main cameras,
we hope that they're being caught
on these little things.
Good.
As the crew up their spying efforts,
the guards take them
to a promising lead.
Nothing attracts tigers
like a rhino carcass.
It's very fresh.
It's like from the morning. And
it looks like there's a tiger cub.
So there should be
a tigress with cubs
coming to feed on this rhino
carcass. That's pretty cool.
Chadden decides to give
the camera traps one last chance.
If there are tigers around,
they might scare away
the mystery vandals.
Elsewhere in the park,
the security cameras are turning up
some unexpected results.
The night-time... Yeah.
Survived another... Ooh!
It's a bear!
Well, that's a very rare sighting.
I've never seen a bear in Kaziranga.
Haven't you? In all my years, never.
Oh, his fingernails...
Look at those, look at his claws.
Right on the lens.
So, I thought
this was elephant damage.
I never thought we'd see
a sloth bear doing that.
A return to the rhino carcass
and the plot thickens.
Our transmitter's gone.
That's what tigers think of
camera traps.
There's a bit over there, pieces.
The security cameras
have caught a new culprit.
Oh, my goodness!
There they are. Oh!
There's the tigress, see that?
It's a tigress. Oh, it snarled
at the camera trap. Look at that!
Sure don't like camera traps.
OK.
With the technology struggling,
Sandesh decides to put himself
on the front line.
And now we're ready.
Time to get the tiger.
He'll have no protection
apart from a thin wall of grass
and must hope he's as well hidden
as the local wildlife.
Over the next five days,
Sandesh plays the role
of human camera trap.
Eventually, the more
hands-on approach pays off.
Traditional filming methods
and a little bit of patience
have helped reveal
the hidden creatures of Kaziranga.
But it's good to know
there are still wild places
where animals like
to keep their secrets.
EQUIPMENT CREAKS AND THUDS
I knew it was elephants!
Next time,
we venture to
the newest habitat on Earth -
our cities -
to reveal the extraordinary ways
that animals survive
in this man-made world.